<tool id="mds_plot" name="Multi dimensional scaling(MDS)" version="1.0">
    <description>plots to an overview of similarities and differences between samples</description>
    <macros>
        <import>minfi_macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="requirements" />
	<command detect_errors="exit_code">
		Rscript "${mds_plot}"
    </command>
    <configfiles>
        <configfile name="mds_plot"><![CDATA[
### code chunk: Load all required libraries quietly
library('minfi', quietly=TRUE, warn.conflicts=FALSE,verbose = FALSE)

## Load the RGset data
if(!is.null("${RGset}")){
    load("${RGset}")
}

## Set phenotype data
pd = pData(RGset)
files = gsub(".+/","",pd\$filenames)
maintitle=as.character("${mainTitle}")
numPositions=as.integer("${numPositions}")

## Produce PDF file
if (!is.null("${pdffile}")) {
    ## Make PDF of density plot
    pdf("${pdffile}")
    minfi::mdsPlot(dat=RGset,sampNames=files,sampGroups=pd\$status,main=maintitle,numPositions=numPositions,pch=19)
    dev.off()
}
        ]]></configfile>
    </configfiles>
    <inputs>
        <param name="RGset" type="data" format="RData" label="Input RGset for generating MDS plot" />
        <param name="numPositions" type="integer" value="1000" label="numPositions"/>
        <param name="mainTitle" type="text" value="MDS plot" label="Main title for graph"/>
    </inputs>
	<outputs>
	  <data format="pdf" name="pdffile" label="PDF of MDS plot"/>
	</outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[

**What it does**

After preprocessing the raw data to obtain methylation estimates, Multi-dimensional scaling
(MDS) plots provide a quick way to get a first sense of the relationship between samples.
They are similar to the more familiar PCA plots and display a two-dimensional approximation
of sample-to-sample Euclidean distance. Note that while the plot visualizes the distance
in epigenomic profiles between samples, the absolute positions of the points is not meaningful.
One often expects to see greater between-group than within-group distances (although
this clearly depends on the particular experiment). The most variable locations are used
when calculating sample distances, with the number specified by the numPositions option.

**Input** :

*RGset* is a RGChannelSet object, which contains the raw data from the IDAT files: green intensities and red intensities.

You can generate an RGset for you Illumina 450k arrys (IDAT files) using the tool to "Read Illumina 450k IDAT". You can find detailed
instructions on how to use tool in the help section for the tool.

*numPositions* gives the number of genomic positions with the most methylation variability
when calculating distance between samples. (default value is 1000)

*Main title for grpah* Title of the graph


**Output**:

PDF file of the MDS plot

    ]]></help>
    <expand macro="citations" />
</tool>



