<tool id="hyphy_b_still" name="HyPhy-B-STILL" version="@TOOL_VERSION@+galaxy@VERSION_SUFFIX@" profile="@PROFILE@">
    <description>Bayesian Significance Test of Invariant Low Likelihoods</description>
    <macros>
        <import>macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="bio_tools"/>
    <expand macro="requirements"/>
    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        @SYMLINK_FILES@
        hyphy b-still
            --alignment ./$input_file
            @INPUT_TREE@
            --code '$gencodeid'
            --method '$posteriorEstimationMethod.method'
            @posteriorEstimationMethod_cmd@
            --grid '$advanced_options.grid_points'
            --concentration_parameter '$advanced_options.concentration'
            --non-zero $advanced_options.non_zero
            --ebf '$advanced_options.ebf'
            --radius-threshold '$advanced_options.radius_threshold'
            --kill-zero-lengths $advanced_options.kill_zero_lengths
            --output '$b_still_output'
            > b_still_stdout.md 
        @ERRORS@
    ]]></command>
    <inputs>
        <expand macro="inputs"/>
        <expand macro="gencode"/>
        <expand macro="conditional_posteriorEstimationMethod" />
        <section name="advanced_options" title="Advanced Options" expanded="false">
            <param argument="--grid"  type="integer" value="20" min="5" max="50" label="Grid points" help="The number of grid points used to approximate the posterior distribution of dN and dS." />
            <param argument="--concentration_parameter" name="concentration" type="float" value="0.5" min="0.001" max="1" label="Concentration parameter of the Dirichlet prior" help="The concentration parameter of the Dirichlet prior on the grid weights." />
            <param argument="--non-zero" type="boolean" truevalue="Yes" falsevalue="No" label="Enforce non-zero synonymous rates" help="Enforce non-zero synonymous rates on the grid. This is useful for calculating dN/dS ratios, as it prevents division by zero."/>
            <param argument="--ebf" type="float" value="10" min="0" max="10000" label="EBF threshold for reporting proximal invariance" help="Empirical Bayes Factor threshold for reporting sites under proximal constraint." />
            <param argument="--radius-threshold" name="radius_threshold" type="float" value="0.5" min="0" max="10" label="Expected substitution multiplier for defining 'near-zero' selective regime" help="Defines the radius threshold for considering a site as proximal to invariance." />
            <expand macro="kill_zero_lengths_param"/>
        </section>

    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="b_still_output" format="hyphy_results.json" />
        <data name="b_still_md_report" format="markdown" from_work_dir="b_still_stdout.md" label="B-STILL Report (Markdown) for ${tool.name} on ${on_string}" />
    </outputs>
    <tests>
        <test expect_num_outputs="2">
            <param name="input_file" ftype="fasta.gz" value="fubar-in1.fa.gz"/>
            <param name="input_nhx" ftype="nhx" value="fubar-in1.nhx"/>
            <conditional name="posteriorEstimationMethod">
                <param name="method" value="Variational-Bayes"/>
            </conditional>
            <output name="b_still_output">
                <assert_contents>
                    <has_text text="B-STILL"/>
                </assert_contents>
            </output>
            <output name="b_still_md_report">
                <assert_contents>
                    <has_text text="B-STILL"/>
                </assert_contents>
            </output>
        </test>
    </tests>
    <help><![CDATA[

B-STILL : Bayesian Significance Test of Invariant Low Likelihoods
==================================================================

What question does this method answer?
--------------------------------------

Which sites in a gene are effectively invariant (alpha=beta=0) or proximal to invariance, indicating sites under strong functional constraint or experiencing negligible evolutionary change?

Recommended Applications
------------------------

B-STILL is designed to identify sites that show minimal to no evolutionary change across the phylogeny. This is particularly useful for:

- Identifying functionally constrained sites that are critical for protein structure or function
- Detecting sites under extreme purifying selection
- Characterizing regions of genes that are evolutionarily "frozen"
- Complementing positive selection analyses by identifying the most conserved sites

Brief description
-----------------

B-STILL (Bayesian Significance Test of Invariant Low Likelihoods) is a modified version of FUBAR that focuses on detecting invariant sites. It uses a denser grid around zero and reports the posterior probability and Empirical Bayes Factor for sites being effectively invariant (alpha=beta=0) or proximal to invariance.

The method models non-synonymous (dN) and synonymous (dS) substitution rates at each site using a Bayesian approach with a discretized grid. Unlike standard FUBAR which focuses on detecting positive selection (dN/dS > 1), B-STILL emphasizes the detection of sites where both rates are near or at zero.

B-STILL offers three different methods for estimating the posterior distribution:

*   **Variational-Bayes:** A fast approximation method that is the recommended default.
*   **Collapsed-Gibbs:** A faster MCMC method.
*   **Metropolis-Hastings:** The original, slowest MCMC method.

Input
-----

1. A *FASTA* sequence alignment.
2. A phylogenetic tree in the *Newick* format

Note: the names of sequences in the alignment must match the names of the sequences in the tree.


Output
------

A JSON file with analysis results (http://hyphy.org/resources/json-fields.pdf).

A markdown report with sites identified as invariant or proximal to invariance.

Further reading
---------------

http://hyphy.org/methods/selection-methods/#FUBAR


Tool options
------------
::


    --code             Which genetic code to use

    --grid             The number of grid points used to approximate the posterior distribution of dN and dS. A larger grid will provide a more accurate approximation but will also be slower. The default value of 20 is a good compromise between speed and accuracy.

    --method           The inference method to use for estimating the posterior distribution.
                            Variational-Bayes : 0-th order Variational Bayes approximation; fastest [default]
                            Metropolis-Hastings : Full Metropolis-Hastings MCMC algorithm; orignal method [slowest]
                            Collapsed-Gibbs  : Collapsed Gibbs sampler [intermediate speed]


    --chains           The number of MCMC chains to run. This is only applicable to the Metropolis-Hastings and Collapsed-Gibbs methods. A larger number of chains will provide a better exploration of the posterior distribution but will also be slower.
                            default value: 5

    --chain-length     The length of each MCMC chain. This is only applicable to the Metropolis-Hastings and Collapsed-Gibbs methods. A longer chain will provide a better exploration of the posterior distribution but will also be slower.
                            default value: 2,000,000

    --burn-in          The number of samples to discard from the beginning of each MCMC chain. This is done to ensure that the chain has converged to the posterior distribution. This is only applicable to the Metropolis-Hastings and Collapsed-Gibbs methods.
                            default value: 1,000,000

    --samples          The number of samples to draw from each MCMC chain after the burn-in period. These samples are used to estimate the posterior distribution. This is only applicable to the Metropolis-Hastings and Collapsed-Gibbs methods.
                            default value: 1,000

    --concentration_parameter
                        The concentration parameter of the Dirichlet prior on the grid weights.
                        default value: 0.5

    --non-zero          Enforce non-zero synonymous rates on the grid. This is useful for calculating dN/dS ratios, as it prevents division by zero.

    --ebf               Empirical Bayes Factor threshold for reporting sites under proximal constraint.
                        default value: 10

    --radius-threshold  Expected substitution multiplier for defining 'near-zero' selective regime. Defines the radius threshold for considering a site as proximal to invariance.
                        default value: 0.5

    --kill-zero-lengths Automatically delete internal zero-length branches for computational efficiency. This will not affect the results.

    ]]></help>
</tool>
