<tool id="estimate_cell_counts" name="Cell Proportion Estimation" version="1.0">
    <description>across all samples and cell types for 450k data</description>
    <macros>
        <import>minfi_macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="requirements" />
	<command detect_errors="exit_code">
		Rscript "${estimate_cell_count}"
	</command>
    <configfiles>
        <configfile name="estimate_cell_count"><![CDATA[
## Load library

library(minfi, quietly=TRUE, warn.conflicts=FALSE,verbose = FALSE)

## Load the RGset data
if(!is.null("${RGset}")){
    load("${RGset}")
}

## Set phenotype data
pd = pData(RGset)

result = minfi::estimateCellCounts(dat=RGset,meanPlot="${meanplot}")

write.table(result,file="estimated_cell_counts.txt",quote=FALSE,row.names=FALSE)

      ]]></configfile>
    </configfiles>
    <inputs>
        <param name="RGset" type="data" format="RData" label="Input RGset for Estimating Cell counts" />
        <param name="meanPlot" type="boolean" checked="false" truevalue="TRUE" falsevalue="FALSE" label="Plot the average DNA methylation?" />
    </inputs>
	<outputs>
	  <data format="txt" name="output" label="Estimated Cell Counts"/>
	</outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[

**What it does**

Estimates the relative proportion of pure cell types within a sample. For example, given peripheral blood samples, this function will return the relative proportions of lymphocytes, monocytes, B-cells, and neutrophils.

Details:

This is an implementaion of the Houseman et al (2012) regression calibration approachalgorithm
to the Illumina 450k microarray for deconvoluting heterogeneous tissue sources like blood. For
example, this function will take an RGChannelSet from a DNA methylation (DNAm) study of
blood, and return the relative proportions of CD4+ and CD8+ T-cells, natural killer cells, monocytes,
granulocytes, and b-cells in each sample.
The meanPlot should be used to check for large batch effects in the data, reducing the confidence
placed in the composition estimates. This plot depicts the average DNA methylation across the
cell-type discrimating probes in both the provided and sorted data. The means from the provided
heterogeneous samples should be within the range of the sorted samples. If the sample means fall
outside the range of the sorted means, the cell type estimates will inflated to the closest cell type.
Note that we quantile normalize the sorted data with the provided data to reduce these batch effects.

**Input** :

*RGset* is a RGChannelSet object, which contains the raw data from the IDAT files: green intensities and red intensities.

You can generate an RGset for you Illumina 450k arrys (IDAT files) using the tool to "Read Illumina 450k IDAT". You can find detailed
instructions on how to use tool in the help section for the tool.


*meanPlot* Whether to plots the average DNA methylation across the cell-type discrimating
probes within the mixed and sorted samples.

**Output**:

Matrix of composition estimates across all samples and cell types.

    ]]></help>
    <citations>
        <citation type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu049</citation>
        <citation type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-13-86</citation>
        <citation type="doi">10.1186/gb-2014-15-2-r31</citation>
    </citations>
</tool>
