<?xml version="1.0"?>
<macros>
    <token name="@TOOL_VERSION@">15.6f452</token>
    <token name="@VERSION_SUFFIX@">0</token>
    <token name="@PROFILE@">22.05</token>
    <xml name="requirements">
        <requirements>
            <requirement type="package" version="@TOOL_VERSION@">mmseqs2</requirement>
            <yield/>
        </requirements>
    </xml>
    <xml name="xrefs">
        <xrefs>
            <xref type="bio.tools">MMseqs2</xref>
        </xrefs>
    </xml>
    <xml name="citations">
        <citations>
            <citation type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3988</citation>
            <citation type="doi">10.1101/079681</citation>
            <citation type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-04964-5</citation>
            <citation type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty1057</citation>
            <citation type="doi">10.1101/2020.11.27.401018</citation>
            <citation type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btab184</citation>
        </citations>
    </xml>
    <token name="HELP"><![CDATA[
MMseqs2: ultra fast and sensitive sequence search and clustering suite

MMseqs2 (Many-against-Many sequence searching) is a software suite to search and cluster huge protein and nucleotide sequence sets. 
MMseqs2 is open source GPL-licensed software implemented in C++ for Linux, MacOS, and (as beta version, via cygwin) Windows. 
The software is designed to run on multiple cores and servers and exhibits very good scalability. 
MMseqs2 can run 10000 times faster than BLAST. At 100 times its speed it achieves almost the same sensitivity. 
It can perform profile searches with the same sensitivity as PSI-BLAST at over 400 times its speed.

Easy workflows to cluster, search and assign taxonomy are provide.
These easy workflows are a shorthand to deal directly with FASTA/FASTQ files as input and output. 
MMseqs2 provides many modules to transform, filter, execute external programs and search. 
However, these modules use the MMseqs2 database formats, instead of the FASTA/FASTQ format. 
For maximum flexibility, we recommend using MMseqs2 workflows and modules directly. 

**Commands available**

Main workflows for database input/output
    taxonomy              Taxonomic classification

Input database creation
    createdb              Convert FASTA/Q file(s) to a sequence DB

Format conversion for downstream processing
    createtsv             Convert result DB to tab-separated flat file

    ]]></token>
</macros>