<tool id="mmseqs2_taxonomy_assignment" name="MMseqs2 Taxonomy Assignment" version="@TOOL_VERSION@+galaxy@VERSION_SUFFIX@" profile="@PROFILE@">
    <description>
        Assigns taxonomic labels to sequences by comparing them to a reference database and identifying the lowest common ancestor
    </description>
    <macros>
        <import>macro.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="biotools"/>
    <expand macro="requirements"/>
    <expand macro="version_command"/>
    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[

    ]]></command>
    <inputs>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
    </outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[
**MMseqs2: ultra fast and sensitive sequence search and clustering suite**

MMseqs2 (Many-against-Many sequence searching) is a software suite to search and cluster huge protein and nucleotide sequence sets. 
MMseqs2 is open source GPL-licensed software implemented in C++ for Linux, MacOS, and (as beta version, via cygwin) Windows. 
The software is designed to run on multiple cores and servers and exhibits very good scalability. 
MMseqs2 can run 10000 times faster than BLAST. At 100 times its speed it achieves almost the same sensitivity. 
It can perform profile searches with the same sensitivity as PSI-BLAST at over 400 times its speed.

**Usage** 

* Convert FASTA/Q file(s) to MMseqs sequence DB format
    *mmseqs createdb <i:fastaFile1[.gz|.bz2]> ... <i:fastaFileN[.gz|.bz2]>|<i:stdin> <o:sequenceDB> [options]*

* Add taxonomic labels to sequence DB
    *mmseqs createtaxdb <i:sequenceDB> <tmpDir> [options]*

* Filter taxonomy sequence database
    *mmseqs filtertaxseqdb <i:taxSeqDB> <o:taxSeqDB> [options]*

* Taxonomy assignment by computing the lowest common ancestor of homologs
    *mmseqs taxonomy <i:queryDB> <i:targetDB> <o:taxaDB> <tmpDir> [options]*

* Convert result DB to tab-separated flat file
    *mmseqs createtsv <i:queryDB> [<i:targetDB>] <i:resultDB> <o:tsvFile> [options]*

* Create a taxonomy report in Kraken or Krona format
    *mmseqs taxonomyreport <i:seqTaxDB> <i:taxResultDB/resultDB/sequenceDB> <o:taxonomyReport> [options]*

By Martin Steinegger <martin.steinegger@snu.ac.kr> & Milot Mirdita <milot@mirdita.de> & Florian Breitwieser <florian.bw@gmail.com> & Eli Levy Karin <eli.levy.karin@gmail.com>

-----

**References**

- Steinegger M, Soding J: MMseqs2 enables sensitive protein sequence searching for the analysis of massive data sets. Nature Biotechnology, 35(11), 1026-1028 (2017)
- Mirdita M, Steinegger M, Breitwieser F, Soding J, Levy Karin E: Fast and sensitive taxonomic assignment to metagenomic contigs. Bioinformatics, btab184 (2021)
    ]]></help>
    <expand macro="citations"/>
</tool>