<?xml version="1.0"?>
<macros>
  <token name="@TOOL_VERSION@">1.8.1</token>
  <token name="@VERSION_SUFFIX@">0</token>
  <token name="@PROFILE@">21.05</token>
  <xml name="version_command">
     <version_command><![CDATA[rcf -V]]></version_command>
  </xml>
  <xml name="xrefs">
    <xrefs>
      <xref type='bio.tools'>Recentrifuge</xref>
    </xrefs>
  </xml>
  <xml name="requirements">
    <requirements>
      <requirement type="package" version="@TOOL_VERSION@">recentrifuge</requirement>
    </requirements>
  </xml>
  <xml name="input_database">
    <section name="database" title="Database type" expanded="true">
      <param name="cached_db" label="Cached database with clade-specific marker genes" type="select">
        <options from_data_table="recentrifuge_database">
          <validator message="No recentrifuge database is available" type="no_options" />
        </options>
      </param>
    </section>
  </xml>
  <xml name="citations">
      <citations>
        <citation type="bibtex">
          @article{10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006967,
          doi = {10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006967},
          author = {Martí, Jose Manuel},
          journal = {PLOS Computational Biology},
          publisher = {Public Library of Science},
          title = {Recentrifuge: Robust comparative analysis and contamination removal for metagenomics},
          year = {2019},
          month = {04},
          volume = {15},
          url = {https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006967},
          pages = {1-24},
          abstract = {Metagenomic sequencing is becoming widespread in biomedical and environmental research,
          and the pace is increasing even more thanks to nanopore sequencing. With a rising number of samples and data per sample,
          the challenge of efficiently comparing results within a specimen and between specimens arises. Reagents, laboratory,
          and host related contaminants complicate such analysis.
          Contamination is particularly critical in low microbial biomass body sites and environments, where it can comprise most of a sample if not all.
          Recentrifuge implements a robust method for the removal of negative-control and crossover taxa from the rest of samples.
          With Recentrifuge, researchers can analyze results from taxonomic classifiers using interactive charts
          with emphasis on the confidence level of the classifications. In addition to contamination-subtracted samples,
          Recentrifuge provides shared and exclusive taxa per sample, thus enabling robust contamination removal and comparative analysis
          in environmental and clinical metagenomics. Regarding the first area,
          Recentrifuge’s novel approach has already demonstrated its benefits showing that microbiomes of Arctic and Antarctic solar panels display
           similar taxonomic profiles.
          In the clinical field, to confirm Recentrifuge’s ability to analyze complex metagenomes,
          we challenged it with data coming from a metagenomic investigation of RNA in plasma that suffered from critical
          contamination to the point of preventing any positive conclusion.
          Recentrifuge provided results that yielded new biological insight into the problem, supporting the growing evidence of a
          blood microbiota even in healthy individuals, mostly translocated from the gut, the oral cavity, and the genitourinary tract.
          We also developed a synthetic dataset carefully designed to rate the robust contamination removal algorithm,
          which demonstrated a significant improvement in specificity while retaining a high sensitivity even in the presence of cross-contaminants.
           Recentrifuge’s official website is www.recentrifuge.org.
          The data and source code are anonymously and freely available on GitHub and PyPI.
          The computing code is licensed under the AGPLv3.
          The Recentrifuge Wiki is the most extensive and continually-updated source of documentation for Recentrifuge,
          covering installation, use cases, testing, and other useful topics.},
          number = {4},
          }
        </citation>
      </citations>
  </xml>
</macros>
