<macros>
    <token name="@TOOL_VERSION@">1.1.1</token>
    <token name="@VERSION_SUFFIX@">0</token>
    <xml name="requirements">
        <requirements>
            <requirement type="package" version="@TOOL_VERSION@">baredsc</requirement>
            <requirement type="package" version="1.12">gzip</requirement>
        </requirements>
        <version_command><![CDATA[baredSC_1d --version]]></version_command>
    </xml>
    <xml name="helpcitations">
        <help><![CDATA[

            .. class:: infomark
            
            **BARED (Bayesian Approach to Retreive Expression Distribution of) Single Cell**
            
            baredSC is a tool that uses a Monte-Carlo Markov Chain to estimate a confidence interval on the probability density function (PDF) of expression of one or two genes from single-cell RNA-seq data. It uses the raw counts and the total number of UMI for each cell. The PDF is approximated by a number of 1d or 2d gaussians provided by the user. The likelihood is estimated using the asumption that the raw counts follow a Poisson distribution of parameter equal to the proportion of mRNA for the gene in the cell multiplied by the total number of UMI identified in this cell.
            
            To get a description of outputs, please read the `Documentation <https://baredsc.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html>`_

            This is the figure with the results. 

            - When the 1d version is used, it displays the mean pdf in solid red line, the median in black dashed lines (/!\backslash the integral of the median is not equal to 1) with the confidence interval of 1 sigma (68%), 2 sigma (95%) and 3 sigma (99.7%) as well as in green, the kernel density estimate of the input values, the detected expression (``log(1 + targetSum * raw / total UMI)``).

            - When the 2d version is used, it displays the pdf as a heatmap as well as a projection on the x and y axis. On the projection, the confidence interval 68% is indicated as a shaded area as well as the mean with a solid red line and the median with a dashed black line. On the top right corner, the correlation is indicated with the confidence interval 68% as well as a confidence interval on the one-sided p-value (the probability that the correlation is the opposite sign of the mean, one sigma confidence interval).
            
        ]]></help>
        <citations>
            <citation type="doi">10.1186/s12859-021-04507-8</citation>
        </citations>
    </xml>
    <xml name="edam_topics">
        <edam_topics>
            <edam_topic>topic_3170</edam_topic>
            <edam_topic>topic_4028</edam_topic>
            <edam_topic>topic_2269</edam_topic>
        </edam_topics>
    </xml>
</macros>