<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tool id="td" name="TD:" version="1.0.2" profile="19.01">
    <description>Tag distance analysis of duplex tags</description>
    <macros>
        <import>fsd_macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="requirements" />
    <command><![CDATA[
        python '$__tool_directory__/td.py' 
        --inputFile '${inputFile}' 
        --inputName1 '${inputFile.element_identifier}' 
        --sample_size '${sampleSize}'
        --subset_tag '${subsetTag}'
        --nproc "\${GALAXY_SLOTS:-1}" 
        $onlyDCS 
        $rel_freq
        --minFS '${minFS}' 
        --maxFS '${maxFS}'
        $nr_above_bars 
        --output_pdf '${output_pdf}'
        --output_tabular '${output_tabular}'
        --output_chimeras_tabular '${output_chimeras_tabular}'
    ]]>
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="inputFile" type="data" format="tabular" label="Input tags" optional="false" help="This dataset is generated by post-processing of the output from 'Make Families' or 'Correct Barcodes' tool by extracting the first two columns, sorting the tags (column 1) and adding the counts of unique occurencies of each tag. See Help section below for a detailed explanation."/>
        <param name="sampleSize" type="integer" label="Number of tags to sample" value="1000" min="0" help="A typical duplex experiment contains very large number of tags. To reduce the runtime of this tool it can sample a subset of tags from the dataset. This parameter specifies how many tags to sample. 1000 is a good starting default. Set to '0' to sample all tags."/>
        <param name="minFS" type="integer" label="Minimum family size" min="1" value="1" help="Tags forming families of size smaller than this value will be filtered out. Default = 1"/>
        <param name="maxFS" type="integer" label="Maximum family size" min="0" value="0" help="Tags forming families of size larger than this value will be filtered out. Set to '0' to turn off this restriction. Default = 0"/>
        <param name="onlyDCS" type="boolean" label="Include only DCS in the analysis?" truevalue="" falsevalue="--only_DCS" checked="False" help="Include only tags forming duplex families (e.g. present in ab and ba configurations)."/>
        <param name="rel_freq" type="boolean" label="Relative frequency" truevalue="" falsevalue="--rel_freq" checked="False" help="If True, the relative frequencies instead of the absolute values are displayed in the plots."/>
        <param name="subsetTag" type="integer" label="Shorten tag in the analysis?" value="0" help="Use this parameter to simulate shorted tag lengths. Set to '0' to keep the original length. Default = 0"/>
        <param name="nproc" type="integer" label="Number of processors" value="8" help="Number of processor used for computing."/>
        <param name="nr_above_bars" type="boolean" label="Include numbers above bars?" truevalue="--nr_above_bars" falsevalue="" checked="True" help="The absolute and relative values of the data can be included or removed from the plots. "/>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="output_tabular" format="tabular" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: Summary"/>
        <data name="output_chimeras_tabular" format="tabular" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: Tags of chimeras"/>
        <data name="output_pdf" format="pdf" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: PDF" />
    </outputs>
    <tests>
        <test>
            <param name="inputFile" value="td_data.tab"/>
            <param name="sampleSize" value="0"/>
            <output name="output_pdf" file="td_output.pdf" lines_diff="136" />
            <output name="output_tabular" file="td_output.tab" />
            <output name="output_chimeras_tabular" file="td_chimeras_output.tab" lines_diff="2"/>
        </test>
    </tests>
    <help> <![CDATA[
**What it does**

Tags used in Duplex Sequencing (DS) are randomized barcodes, e.g 12 base pairs long. Since each DNA fragment is labeled by two tags at each end there are theoretically 4 to the power of (12+12) unique combinations. However, the input DNA in a typical DS experiment contains only ~1,000,000 molecules creating a large tag-to-input excess (4^24
≫ 1,000,000). Because of such excess it is highly unlikely to tag distinct input DNA molecules with highly similar barcodes.

This tool calculates the number of nucleotide differences among tags (tag distance), also known as `Hamming distance <https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamming_distance>`_. In this context the Hamming distance is simply the number of differences between two tags. The tool compares in a randomly selected subset of tags (default n=1000), the difference between each tag of the subset with the tags of the complete dataset. Each tag will differ by a certain number of nucleotides with the other tags; yet the tool uses the smallest difference observed with any other tag.
    
**Input**
    
This tools expects a tabular file with the tags of all families, the family sizes and information about forward (ab) and reverse (ba) strands::

 1 2                        3
 -----------------------------
 1 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAATGGTATG ba
 3 AAAAAAAAAAAAAATGGTATGGAC ab

.. class:: infomark

**How to generate the input**

The first step of the `Du Novo Analysis Pipeline <https://doi.org/10.1186/s13059-016-1039-4>`_ is the **Make Families** tool or the **Correct Barcodes** tool that produces output in this form::

 1                        2  3     4
 ------------------------------------------------------
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab read1 CGCTACGTGACTGGGTCATG
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab read2 CGCTACGTGACTGGGTCATG
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab read3 CGCTACGTGACTGGGTCATG
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAATGGTATG ba read3 CGCTACGTGACTAAAACATG

We only need columns 1 and 2. These two columns can be extracted from this dataset using the **Cut** tool::

 1                        2 
 ---------------------------
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAATGGTATG ba

Next, the tags are sorted in ascending or descending order using the **Sort** tool::

 1                        2 
 ---------------------------
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAATGGTATG ba
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab
 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAATAGCTCGAT ab

Finally, unique occurencies of each tag are counted. This is done using **Unique lines** tool that adds an additional column with the counts that also represent the family size (column 1)::

 1 2                        3
 -----------------------------
 1 AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAATGGTATG ba
 3 AAAAAAAAAAAAAATGGTATGGAC ab

These data can now be used in this tool.
    
**Output**
    
The output is one PDF file with various plots of the tag distance, a tabular file with the summarized data of the plots and a tabular file with the chimeras. The PDF file contains several pages:

 1. This first page contains a graph representing the minimum tag distance (smallest number of differences) categorized after the family sizes.
 
 2. The second page contains the same information as the first page, but plots the family size categorized by the minimum tag distance.
 
 3. The third page contains the **first step** of the **chimera analysis**, which examines the differences between the tags at both ends of a read (a/b). Chimeras can be distinguished by carrying the same tag at one end combined with multiple different tags at the other end of a read. Here, we describe the calculation of the TDs for only one tag in detail, but the process is repeated for each tag in the sample (default n=1000). First, the tool splits the tag into its upstream and downstream part (named a and b) and compares it with all other a parts of the families in the dataset. Next, the tool estimates the sequence differences (TD) among the a parts and extracts those tags with the smallest difference (TD a.min) and calculates the TD of the b part. The tags with the largest differences are extracted to estimate the maximum TD (TD b.max). The process is repeated starting with the b part instead and estimates TD a.max and TD b.min. Next, we calculate the sum of TD a.min and TD b.max.
 
 4. The fourth page contains the **second step** of the **chimera analysis**: the absolute difference (=delta TD) between the partial TDs (TD a.min & TD b.max and TD b.min & TD a.max). The partial TDs of chimeric tags are normally very different which means that multiple combinations of the same a part with different b parts are likely. But it is possible that small delta TDs occur due to a half of a tag that is identical to other halves in the data. For this purpose, the relative difference between the partial TDs is estimated in the next step.

 5. The fifth page contains the **third step** of the **chimera analysis**: the relative differences of the partial TDs (=relative delta TD). These are calculated as the absolute difference between TD a.min and TD b.max equal to TD delta. Since it is not known whether the absolute difference originates due to a low and a very large TD within a tag or an identical half (TD=0), the tool estimates the relative TD delta as the ratio of the difference to the sum of the partial TDs. In a chimera, it is expected that only one end of the tag contributes to the TD of the whole tag. In other words, if the same a part is observed in combination with several different b parts, then one end will have a TD = 0. Thus, the TD difference between the parts (TD a.min - TD b.max, TD a.max - TD b.min) is the same as the sum of the parts (TD a.min + TD b.max, TD a.max + TD b.min) or the ratio of the difference to the sum (relative delta TD = TD a.min - TD b.max / (TD a.min + TD b.max or TD a.max - TD b.min / (TD a.max + TD b.min)) will equal 1 in chimeric families. Here, the maximum value of the relative delta TD and the respective delta TD (in step 4) are selected and the plot can be interpreted as the following:

    - A low relative difference indicates that the total TD is equally distributed in the two partial TDs. This case would be expected, if all tags originate from different molecules.
    - A relative delta TD of 1 means that one part of the tags is identical. Since it is very unlikely that by chance two different tags have a TD of 0, the TDs in the other half are probably artificially introduced and represents chimeric families.

 6. The sixth page is an analysis only of **chimeric tags** (relative delta TD =1) from step 5.

 7. The last page is only generated when the parameter **"Include only DCS in the analysis?"** is set to **False (NO)**. The graph represents the **TD of the chimeric tags** that form a DCS (complementary ab and ba).

 .. class:: infomark

**Note:** 
Chimeras can be identical in the first or second part of the tag and can have an identical TD with mutliple tags. Therefore, the second column of the output file can have multiple tag entries. The file also contains the family sizes and the direction of the read (ab, ba). The asterisks mark the identical part of the tag::

 1                                      2
 --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
 GAAAGGGAGG GCGCTTCACG	1 ba            GCAATCGACG *GCGCTTCACG* 1 ba
 CCCTCCCTGA GGTTCGTTAT	1 ba            CGTCCTTTTC *GGTTCGTTAT* 1 ba, GCACCTCCTT *GGTTCGTTAT* 1  ba
 ATGCTGATCT CGAATGCATA	55 ba, 59 ab    AGGTGCCGCC *CGAATGCATA* 27 ba, *ATGCTGATCT* GAATGTTTAC 1 ba
   ]]> 
    </help>
    <expand macro="citation" />
</tool>

