<tool id="minfi_bumphunter" name="Bumphunter" version="0.1.0">
    <description>to estimate differentially methylated regions</description>
    <macros>
        <import>minfi_macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="requirements" />
    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        Rscript bumphunter_script.R --RGset=$RGset --preprocess=$preprocess --cores="\${GALAXY_SLOTS:-4}"
        ]]>
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param type="data" name="RGset" format="rdata" label="Input RGset in the RData format"/>
        <conditional name="preprocess">
           <param name="preprocess_method" type="select" label="Select Preprocessing Method">
              <option value="pre_normalized">My data is already normalized</option>
              <option value="quantile">Quantile Normalization</option>
              <option value="raw">Raw Normalization</option>
              <option value="noob">Noob Normalization</option>
           </param>
        </conditional>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="dmrs" format="csv" from_work_dir="bumps.csv" />
        <data name="dmrs_rdata" format="rdata" from_work_dir="bumps.rdata" />
    </outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[

**What it does**

Estimate regions for which a genomic profile deviates from its
baseline value. Originally implemented to detect differentially
methylated genomic regions between two populations.

Details:

This function performs the bumphunting approach described by Jaffe
et al. International Journal of Epidemiology (2012). The main
output is a table of candidate regions with permutation or
bootstrap-based family-wide error rates (FWER) and p-values
assigned.

The general idea is that for each genomic location we have a value
for several individuals. We also have covariates for each
individual and perform regression. This gives us one estimate of
the coefficient of interest (a common example is case versus
control). These estimates are then (optionally) smoothed. The
smoothing occurs in clusters of locations that are ‘close enough’.
This gives us an estimate of a genomic profile that is 0 when
uninteresting. We then take values above (in absolute value)
‘cutoff’ as candidate regions. Permutations can then performed to
create null distributions for the candidate regions.

**Input:**

*RGset* is a RGChannelSet object, which contains the raw data from the IDAT files: green intensities and red intensities.

*Preprocess Method* : Normalization method, please refer to https://www.bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/manuals/minfi/man/minfi.pdf for more
information on the normalization methods.

**Output:**

An object of class ‘bumps’ with the following components:

tab: The table with candidate regions and annotation for these.

coef: The single loci coefficients.

fitted: The estimated genomic profile used to determine the regions.

pvaluesMarginal: marginal p-value for each genomic location.

null: The null distribution.

algorithm: details on the algorithm.

    ]]></help>
    <expand macro="citations" />
</tool>
