<macros>
    <xml name="help">
        <help>
IQ-TREE
=======


The full documentation can be found here_.

.. _here : http://www.iqtree.org/doc/

Beginner's tutorial
===================


Input data
----------

IQ-TREE takes as input a *multiple sequence alignment* and will reconstruct an evolutionary tree that is best explained by the input data. The input alignment can be in various common formats. For example the PHYLIP_ format which may look like:

.. _PHYLIP: http://evolution.genetics.washington.edu/phylip/doc/sequence.html

::

    7 28
    Frog       AAATTTGGTCCTGTGATTCAGCAGTGAT
    Turtle     CTTCCACACCCCAGGACTCAGCAGTGAT
    Bird       CTACCACACCCCAGGACTCAGCAGTAAT
    Human      CTACCACACCCCAGGAAACAGCAGTGAT
    Cow        CTACCACACCCCAGGAAACAGCAGTGAC
    Whale      CTACCACGCCCCAGGACACAGCAGTGAT
    Mouse      CTACCACACCCCAGGACTCAGCAGTGAT

This tiny alignment contains 7 DNA sequences from several animals with the sequence length of 28 nucleotides. IQ-TREE also supports other file formats such as FASTA, NEXUS, CLUSTALW. The FASTA file for the above example may look like this:

::

    >Frog       
    AAATTTGGTCCTGTGATTCAGCAGTGAT
    >Turtle     
    CTTCCACACCCCAGGACTCAGCAGTGAT
    >Bird       
    CTACCACACCCCAGGACTCAGCAGTAAT
    >Human      
    CTACCACACCCCAGGAAACAGCAGTGAT
    >Cow        
    CTACCACACCCCAGGAAACAGCAGTGAC
    >Whale      
    CTACCACGCCCCAGGACACAGCAGTGAT
    >Mouse      
    CTACCACACCCCAGGACTCAGCAGTGAT
    
**NOTE**: If you have raw sequences, you need to first apply alignment programs like MAFFT_ or ClustalW_ to align the sequences, before feeding them into IQ-TREE.

.. _MAFFT: http://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/software/
.. _ClustalW: http://www.clustal.org


First running example
---------------------

From the download_ there is an example alignment called `example.phy`
in PHYLIP format. This example contains parts of the mitochondrial DNA sequences of several animals (Source: `Phylogenetic Handbook`_)

.. _`Phylogenetic Handbook` : http://www.kuleuven.be/aidslab/phylogenybook/home.html)).
.. _download: http://www.iqtree.org/#download

You can now start to reconstruct a maximum-likelihood tree
from this alignment by entering (assuming that you are now in the same folder with `example.phy`):

::

  iqtree -s example.phy


`-s` is the option to specify the name of the alignment file that is always required by
IQ-TREE to work. At the end of the run IQ-TREE will write several output files including:

* `example.phy.iqtree`: the main report file that is self-readable. You should look at this file to see the computational results. It also contains a textual representation of the final tree (see below).

* `example.phy.treefile`: the ML tree in NEWICK format, which can be visualized by any supported tree viewer programs like FigTree or  iTOL.

* `example.phy.log`: log file of the entire run (also printed on the screen). To report bugs, please send this log file and the original alignment file to the authors.

**NOTE**: Starting with version 1.5.4, with this simple command IQ-TREE will by default perform ModelFinder to find the best-fit substitution model and then infer a phylogenetic tree using the selected model.

For this example data the resulting maximum-likelihood tree may look like this (extracted from `.iqtree` file):

**NOTE**: Tree is UNROOTED although outgroup taxon 'LngfishAu' is drawn at root

::

    +--------------LngfishAu
    |
    |        +--------------LngfishSA
    +--------|
    |        +--------------LngfishAf
    |
    |      +-------------------Frog
    +------|
    |               +-----------------Turtle
    |         +-----|
    |         |     |      +-----------------------Sphenodon
    |         |     |   +--|
    |         |     |   |  +--------------------------Lizard
    |         |     +---|
    |         |         |      +---------------------Crocodile
    |         |         +------|
    |         |                +------------------Bird
    +---------|
    |                  +----------------Human
    |               +--|
    |               |  |  +--------Seal
    |               |  +--|
    |               |     |   +-------Cow
    |               |     +---|
    |               |         +---------Whale
    |          +----|
    |          |    |         +------Mouse
    |          |    +---------|
    |          |              +--------Rat
    +----------|
    |   +----------------Platypus
    +---|
    +-------------Opossum    


This makes sense as the mammals (`Human` to `Opossum`) form a clade, whereas the reptiles `Turtle` to `Crocodile`) and `Bird` form a separate sister clade. Here the tree is drawn at the *outgroup* Lungfish which is more accient than other species in this example. However, please note that IQ-TREE always produces an **unrooted tree** as it knows nothing about this biological background; IQ-TREE simply draws the tree this way as `LngfishAu` is the first sequence occuring in the alignment.

Choosing the right substitution model
-------------------------------------

**NOTE**: If you use model selection please cite the following paper:

  __S. Kalyaanamoorthy, B.Q. Minh, T.K.F. Wong, A. von Haeseler, and L.S. Jermiin (2017) ModelFinder: fast model selection for accurate phylogenetic estimates. Nat. Methods, 14:587–589. DOI: 10.1038/nmeth.4285

IQ-TREE supports a wide range of substitution models for DNA, protein, codon, binary and morphological alignments. If you do not know which model is appropriate for your data, you can use ModelFinder to determine the best-fit model:

::

   iqtree -s example.phy -m MFP


`-m` is the option to specify the model name to use during the analysis. The special `MFP` key word stands for *ModelFinder Plus*, which tells IQ-TREE to perform ModelFinder and the remaining analysis using the selected model. ModelFinder computes the log-likelihoods
of an initial parsimony tree for many different models and the *Akaike information criterion* (AIC), *corrected Akaike information criterion* (AICc), and the *Bayesian information criterion* (BIC).
Then ModelFinder chooses the model that minimizes the BIC score (you can also change to AIC or AICc by adding the option `-AIC` or `-AICc`, respectively).

**TIP**: Starting with version 1.5.4, `-m MFP` is the default behavior. Thus, this run is equivalent to

::

 iqtree -s example.phy


If you now look at `example.phy.iqtree` you will see that IQ-TREE selected `TIM2+I+G4` as the best-fit model for this example data. Thus, for additional analyses you do not have to perform the model test again and can use the selected model:

::

  iqtree -s example.phy -m TIM2+I+G

Sometimes you only want to find the best-fit model without doing tree reconstruction, then run:

::

  iqtree -s example.phy -m MF


**Why ModelFinder?**

- ModelFinder is up to 100 times faster than jModelTest/ProtTest.

- jModelTest/ProtTest provides the invariable (`+I`) and Gamma rate (`+G`) heterogeneity across sites, but there is no reason to believe that evolution follows a Gamma distribution. ModelFinder additionally considers the FreeRate heterogeneity model (`+R`), which relaxes the assumption of Gamma distribution, where the site rates and proportions are free-to-vary and inferred independently from the data. Moreover, `+R` allows to automatically determine the number of rate categories, which is impossible with `+G`. This can be important especially for phylogenomic data, where the default 4 rate categories may "underfit" the data.

- ModelFinder works transparently with tree inference in IQ-TREE, thus combining both steps in just one single run! This eliminates the need for a separate software for DNA (jModelTest) and another for protein sequences (ProtTest).

- Apart from DNA and protein sequences, ModelFinder also works with codon, binary and morphological sequences.

- ModelFinder can also find best partitioning scheme just like PartitionFinder (Lanfear et al., 2012).

If you still want to resembles jModelTest/ProtTest, then use option `-m TEST` or `-m TESTONLY` instead.


By default, the maximum number of categories is limitted to 10 due to computational reasons. If your sequence alignment is long enough, then you can increase this upper limit with the `cmax` option:

::

  iqtree -s example.phy -m MF -cmax 15

will test `+R2` to `+R15` instead of at most `+R10`.

To reduce computational burden, one can use the option `-mset` to restrict the testing procedure to a subset of base models instead of testing the entire set of all available models. For example, `-mset WAG,LG` will test only models like `WAG+...` or `LG+...`. Another useful option in this respect is `-msub` for AA data sets. With `-msub nuclear` only general AA models are included, whereas with `-msub viral` only AA models for viruses are included.

If you have enough computational resource, you can perform a thorough and more accurate analysis that invokes a full tree search for each model considered via the `-mtree` option:

::

  iqtree -s example.phy -m MF -mtree



Using codon models
------------------

IQ-TREE supports a number of codon models. You need to input a protein-coding DNA alignment and specify codon data by option `-st CODON` (Otherwise, IQ-TREE applies DNA model because it detects that your alignment has DNA sequences):

::

  iqtree -s coding_gene.phy -st CODON 

If your alignment length is not divisible by 3, IQ-TREE will stop with an error message. IQ-TREE will group sites 1,2,3 into codon site 1; sites 4,5,6 to codon site 2; etc. Moreover, any codon, which has at least one gap/unknown/ambiguous nucleotide, will be treated as unknown codon character.

Note that the above command assumes the standard genetic code. If your sequences follow 'The Invertebrate Mitochondrial Code', then run:

::
  
   iqtree -s coding_gene.phy -st CODON5 

Note that ModelFinder works for codon alignments. IQ-TREE version >= 1.5.4 will automatically invokes ModelFinder to find the best-fit codon model.


Binary, morphological and SNP data
----------------------------------

IQ-TREE supports discrete morphological alignments by  `-st MORPH` option:

::

  iqtree -s morphology.phy -st MORPH

IQ-TREE implements to two morphological ML models: MK and ORDERED.

Morphological data typically do not have constant (uninformative) sites. 
In such cases, you should apply ascertainment bias correction model by e.g.:

::

  iqtree -s morphology.phy -st MORPH -m MK+ASC

You can again select the best-fit binary/morphological model:

::

   iqtree -s morphology.phy -st MORPH


For SNP data (DNA) that typically do not contain constant sites, you can explicitly tell the model to include ascertainment bias correction:

::

  iqtree -s SNP_data.phy -m GTR+ASC

You can explicitly tell model testing to only include `+ASC` model with:

::

  iqtree -s SNP_data.phy -m MFP+ASC


Assessing branch supports with ultrafast bootstrap approximation
----------------------------------------------------------------

To overcome the computational burden required by the nonparametric bootstrap, IQ-TREE introduces an ultrafast bootstrap approximation (UFBoot) ([Minh et al., 2013]) that is  orders of magnitude faster than the standard procedure and provides relatively unbiased branch support values. Citation for UFBoot:

   B.Q. Minh, M.A.T. Nguyen, and A. von Haeseler (2013) Ultrafast approximation for phylogenetic bootstrap. _Mol. Biol. Evol., 30:1188-1195. 


To run UFBoot, use the option  `-bb`:

::

   iqtree -s example.phy -m TIM2+I+G -bb 1000

`-bb`  specifies the number of bootstrap replicates where 1000
is the minimum number recommended. The section  `MAXIMUM LIKELIHOOD TREE` in  `example.phy.iqtree` shows a textual representation of the maximum likelihood tree with branch support values in percentage. The NEWICK format of the tree is printed to the file  `example.phy.treefile`. In addition, IQ-TREE writes the following files:

* `example.phy.contree`: the consensus tree with assigned branch supports where branch lengths are optimized  on the original alignment.

* `example.phy.splits`: support values in percentage for all splits (bipartitions), computed as the occurence frequencies in the bootstrap trees. This file is in "star-dot" format.

* `example.phy.splits.nex`: has the same information as `example.phy.splits` but in NEXUS format, which can be viewed with the program SplitsTree_ to explore the conflicting signals in the data. So it is more informative than consensus tree, e.g. you can see how highly supported the second best conflicting split is, which had no chance to enter the consensus tree.

.. _SplitsTree: http://www.splitstree.org


Reducing impact of severe model violations with UFBoot
------------------------------------------------------

Starting with IQ-TREE version 1.6 we provide a new option `-bnni` to reduce the risk of overestimating branch supports with UFBoot due to severe model violations. With this option UFBoot will further optimize each bootstrap tree using a hill-climbing nearest neighbor interchange (NNI) search based directly on the corresponding bootstrap alignment.

Thus, if severe model violations are present in the data set at hand, users are advised to append `-bnni` to the regular UFBoot command:

iqtree -s example.phy -m TIM2+I+G -bb 1000 -bnni

For more details see:

  D.T. Hoang, O. Chernomor, A. von Haeseler, B.Q. Minh, L.S. Vinh (2017) UFBoot2: Improving the ultrafast bootstrap approximation.


Assessing branch supports with  standard nonparametric bootstrap
----------------------------------------------------------------

The standard nonparametric bootstrap is invoked by  the  `-b` option:

iqtree -s example.phy -m TIM2+I+G -b 100

`-b` specifies the number of bootstrap replicates where 100
is the minimum recommended number. The output files are similar to those produced by the UFBoot procedure. 



Assessing branch supports with single branch tests
--------------------------------------------------

IQ-TREE provides an implementation of the SH-like approximate likelihood ratio test ([Guindon et al., 2010]). To perform this test,  run:

::

  iqtree -s example.phy -m TIM2+I+G -alrt 1000

`-alrt` specifies the number of bootstrap replicates for SH-aLRT where 1000 is the minimum number recommended. 

IQ-TREE also supports other tests such as the aBayes test (Anisimova et al., 2011) and the local bootstrap test (Adachi and Hasegawa, 1996).

You can also perform both SH-aLRT and the ultrafast bootstrap within one single run:

::

  iqtree -s example.phy -m TIM2+I+G -alrt 1000 -bb 1000

The branches of the resulting `.treefile` will be assigned with both SH-aLRT and UFBoot support values, which are readable by any tree viewer program like FigTree, Dendroscope or ETE. You can also look at the textual tree figure in `.iqtree` file:

**NOTE**: Tree is UNROOTED although outgroup taxon 'LngfishAu' is drawn at root
Numbers in parentheses are SH-aLRT support (%) / ultrafast bootstrap support (%)

::

    +-------------LngfishAu
    |
    |       +--------------LngfishSA
    +-------| (100/100)
    |       +------------LngfishAf
    |
    |      +--------------------Frog
    +------| (99.8/100)
    |                     +-----------------Turtle
    |                  +--| (85/72)
    |                  |  |    +------------------------Crocodile
    |                  |  +----| (96.5/97)
    |                  |       +------------------Bird
    |               +--| (39/51)
    |               |  +---------------------------Sphenodon
    |         +-----| (98.2/99)
    |         |     +-------------------------------Lizard
    +---------| (100/100)
    |                   +--------------Human
    |                +--| (92.3/93)
    |                |  |  +------Seal
    |                |  +--| (68.3/75)
    |                |     |  +-----Cow
    |                |     +--| (99.7/100)
    |                |        +-------Whale
    |           +----| (99.1/100)
    |           |    |         +---Mouse
    |           |    +---------| (100/100)
    |           |              +------Rat
    +-----------| (100/100)
    |  +--------------Platypus
    +--| (93/98)
    +-----------Opossum


From this figure, the branching patterns within reptiles are poorly supported (e.g. `Sphenodon` with SH-aLRT: 39%, UFBoot: 51% and `Turtle` with SH-aLRT: 85%, UFBoot: 72%) as well as the phylogenetic position of `Seal` within mammals (SH-aLRT: 68.3%, UFBoot: 75%). Other branches appear to be well supported.
 
        </help>
    </xml>
</macros>
