<?xml version="1.0"?>
<macros>
	<token name="@TOOL_VERSION@">2.3</token>	
	<token name="@VERSION_SUFFIX@">galaxy0</token>
	<xml name="requirements">
        <requirements>
            <requirement type="package" version="@TOOL_VERSION@">suppa</requirement>
        </requirements>
    </xml>
	<xml name="version_command">
       	<!-- no version parameter available -->
        <version_command><![CDATA[conda list suppa 2>&1 | grep 'suppa' | awk -F ' ' '{print$2}']]></version_command>
    </xml>
    <xml name="citations">
        <citations>
	        <citation type="doi">10.1186/s13059-018-1417-1</citation>
	        <citation type="doi">10.1261/rna.051557.115</citation>
	        <citation type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1392</citation>
        </citations>
    </xml>

	<!--
		input
	-->



    <!-- 
		Help
    -->

    <token name="@WID@"><![CDATA[
SUPPA is a flexible and powerful tool to study splicing at the transcript isoform or at the local alternative splicing event level, across multiple conditions and at high speed and accuracy. SUPPA has various modular operations that can be run separately to:

- Generate transcript events and local alternative splicing (AS) events from an annotation
- Quantify transcript and local AS event inclusion levels (PSIs) from multiple samples
- Calculate differential splicing for AS events and differential transcript usage across multiple conditions with replicates
- Cluster events and transcripts according to PSI values across conditions
    ]]></token>
    <token name="@DPSI@"><![CDATA[
A DPSI file contains the information about which events are signficantly differentially spliced in each pairwise comparison. For instance, a dpsi file with data from the comparison of three conditions will look like:

::

    Cond1_Cond2_dPSI  Cond1_Cond2_p-val Cond2_Cond3_dPSI  Cond2_Cond3_p-val
    event1    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>
    event2    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>
    event3    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>    <dpsi_value>
    ]]></token>
    <token name="@PSIVEC@"><![CDATA[
A PSIVEC file contains the PSI values for all samples, either per replicate or the average PSI value per condition, averaging over the replicates.

::

    sample1 sample2 sample3 sample1 sample2 sample3 
    event1    <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value>
    event2    <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value>
    event3    <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value> <psi_value>
    ]]></token>
    <token name="@CLUSTVEC@"><![CDATA[
clustvec is a tab separated file, with the event ID in the first column, the cluster ID as second column, and then followed by a variable even number of fields, one for each condition, giving the mean PSI value per condition. The clustvec file doesn't contain a header. More information are available in the `Cluster analysis <https://github.com/comprna/SUPPA#cluster-analysis>`_ section of the manual.
    ]]></token>
    <token name="@REFERENCES@"><![CDATA[
More information are available on `GitHub <https://github.com/comprna/SUPPA>`_.
	]]></token>
</macros>