<macros>
    <xml name="requirements">
        <requirements>
            <requirement type="package" version="@TOOL_VERSION@">teloscope</requirement>
        </requirements>
    </xml>
    <token name="@TOOL_VERSION@">0.1.2</token>
    <token name="@VERSION_SUFFIX@">0</token>
    <token name="@PROFILE@">23.02</token>
    <xml name="citations">
        <citations>
            <citation type="bibtex">
                @article {Formenti2025.10.14.682431,
                    author = {Formenti, Giulio and Jain, Nivesh and Medico, Jack A. and Sollitto, Marco and Antipov, Dmitry and Barcellos, Suziane and Biegler, Matthew and Borges, In{\^e}s and Chang, J King and Chen, Ying and Cheng, Haoyu and Concei{\c c}{\~a}o, Helena and Davenport, Matthew and De Oliveira, Lorraine and Duarte, Erick and Durham, Gillian and Fenn, Jonathan and Forde, Niamh and Galante, Pedro A. and Gerhardt, Kenji and Giani, Alice M. and Giunta, Simona and Kim, Juhyun and Komissarov, Aleksey and Koo, Bonhwang and Koren, Sergey and Larkin, Denis and Lee, Chul and Li, Heng and Makova, Kateryna and Masterson, Patrick and Murphy, Terence and McCaffrey, Kirsty and Mercuri, Rafael L.V. and Na, Yeojung and O{\textquoteright}Connell, Mary J. and Ou, Shujun and Phillippy, Adam and Popova, Marina and Rhie, Arang and Ruiz-Ruano, Francisco J. and Secomandi, Simona and Smeds, Linn{\'e}a and Suh, Alexander and Tilley, Tatiana and Vontzou, Niki and Waters, Paul D. and Balacco, Jennifer and Jarvis, Erich D.},
                    title = {The complete genome of a songbird},
                    elocation-id = {2025.10.14.682431},
                    year = {2025},
                    doi = {10.1101/2025.10.14.682431},
                    publisher = {Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory},
                    abstract = {Bird genomes are the smallest among amniotes, but remain challenging to assemble due to their structural complexity. This study presents the first fully phased, diploid, telomere-to-telomere (T2T) reference genome for the zebra finch (Taeniopygia guttata), a model organism for neuroscience and evolutionary genomics. Combining multiple sequencing strategies resulted in closing nearly all gaps, adding \~{}90 Mbp of previously missing sequence (7.8\%). This includes T2T assemblies for all microchromosomes, including dot chromosomes, and the previously almost entirely missing chr16. The T2T genome is comprehensively annotated for genes, repeats, structural variants, and long-read methylation calls. Complete centromeric structures were assembled and annotated along with kinetochore binding sites. Relative to the previous high-quality reference of the Vertebrate Genomes Project, 2,778 (8.51\%) previously unassembled or unannotated genes were identified, of which 9\% overlap with segmental duplications. This first complete genome of a songbird, now the new public reference, illuminates avian genome architecture and function.Competing Interest StatementS.K. has received travel funds to speak at events hosted by Oxford Nanopore Technologies.Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council UKHoward Hughes Medical Institute, https://ror.org/006w34k90Leverhulme Trust, RF-2024-492},
                    URL = {https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2025/10/14/2025.10.14.682431},
                    eprint = {https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2025/10/14/2025.10.14.682431.full.pdf},
                    journal = {bioRxiv}
                }
            </citation>
        </citations>
    </xml>
</macros>
